{
  "title": "Discrete_Mathematics - Probability_Theory — Slot 4 (15 Questions)",
  "duration": 42,
  "sections": [
    {
      "name": "Probability_Theory — Slot 4",
      "questions": [
        {
          "id": 1,
          "question": "<p>If the difference between the expectation of the square of random variable \\((E[X^{2}])\\)  and the square of the expectation of the random variable \\((E[X^{2}])\\) is denoted by R then <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2011)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>R=0</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>R\\(\\lt\\)0</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>R\\( \\gt \\)0</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>R\\(\\gt=\\)0</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>R\\(\\gt=\\)0</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2120/gate2011-18#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 2,
          "question": "<p>If two fair coins are flipped and at least one of the outcomes is known to be a\nhead, what is the probability that both outcomes are heads? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2011)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(1/3\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(1/4\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(1/2\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(2/3\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(1/3\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2105/gate2011-3#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 3,
          "question": "<p>What is the probability that divisor of \\(10^{99}\\) is a multiple of \\(10^{96}\\)? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2010)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(1/625\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(4/625\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(12/625\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(16/625\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(1/625\\)</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1153/gate2010-27#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 4,
          "question": "<p>Consider a company that assembles computers. The probability of a faulty assembly of any computer is p. The company therefore subjects each computer to a testing process. This testing process gives the correct result for any computer with a probability of q. What is the probability of a computer being declared faulty? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2010)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>pq + (1 - p) (1 - q)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>(1 - q)p</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>(1 - p) q</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>pq</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>pq + (1 - p) (1 - q)</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1152/gate2010-26#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 5,
          "question": "<p>If the pdf of a Poisson distribution is given by \\(f(x) = \\frac{e^{-2} 2^x}{x!}\\)then its mean is <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2009)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(2^x\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>2</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>-2</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>1</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>2</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/50563/isro2009-66\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 6,
          "question": "<p>Let \\(f(x)\\) be the continuous probability density function of a random variable \\(x\\), the probability that \\(a \\lt x \\leq b\\), is : <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2009)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(f(b-a)\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(f(b) - f(a)\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(\\int\\limits_a^b f(x) dx\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(\\int\\limits_a^b xf (x)dx\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(\\int\\limits_a^b f(x) dx\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1162/gate2005-12-isro2009-64\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 7,
          "question": "<p>An unbalanced dice (with 6 faces, numbered from 1 to 6) is thrown. The\nprobability that the face value is odd is 90% of the probability that the face value\nis even. The probability of getting any even numbered face is the same. <br>\nIf the probability that the face is even given that it is greater than 3 is 0.75,\nwhich one of the following options is closest to the probability that the face value exceeds 3? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2009)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>0.453</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>0.468</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>0.485</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>0.492</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>0.468</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/798/gate2009-21#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 8,
          "question": "<p>What is the probability that in a randomly chosen group of \\(r\\) people at least three people have the same birthday? <br><br><strong>(GATE IT 2008)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(1-\\dfrac{365-364 \\dots (365-r+1)}{365^{r}}\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(\\dfrac{365 \\cdot 364 \\dots (365-r+1)}{365^r}+ ^{r}C_{1}\\cdot 365 \\cdot \\dfrac{364.363 \\dots (364-(r-2)+1)}{364^{r+2} }\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(1- \\dfrac{365 \\cdot 364 \\dots (365-r+1)}{365^{r}} - ^{r}C_{2} \\cdot 365 \\cdot \\dfrac{ 364 \\cdot 363 \\dots (364-(r-2)+1)}{364^{r-2}}\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(\\dfrac{365 \\cdot 364 \\dots (365-r+1)}{365^{r}}\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(1- \\dfrac{365 \\cdot 364 \\dots (365-r+1)}{365^{r}} - ^{r}C_{2} \\cdot 365 \\cdot \\dfrac{ 364 \\cdot 363 \\dots (364-(r-2)+1)}{364^{r-2}}\\)</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/3284/gate2008-it-23\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 9,
          "question": "<p>A sample space has two events A and B such that probabilities <br> \\(P(A\\cap B) = \\dfrac{1}{2}, P(A') = \\dfrac{1}{3}, P(B') =\\dfrac{1}{3}\\). <br> What is \\(P(A\\cup B)\\) ? <br><br><strong>(GATE IT 2008)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(\\left(\\dfrac{11}{12}\\right)\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(\\left(\\dfrac{10}{12}\\right)\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(\\left(\\dfrac{9}{12}\\right)\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(\\left(\\dfrac{8}{12}\\right)\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(\\left(\\dfrac{10}{12}\\right)\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/3224/gate2008-it-2\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 10,
          "question": "<p>Aishwarya studies either computer science or mathematics everyday. If she\nstudies computer science on a day, then the probability that the studies\nmathematics the next day is 0.6. If she studies mathematics on a day, then the\nprobability that the studies computer science the next day is 0.4. Given that\nAishwarya studies computer science on Monday, what is the probability that she\nstudies computer science on Wednesday? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2008)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>0.24</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>0.36</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>0.4</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>0.6</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>0.4</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/425/gate2008-27#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 11,
          "question": "<p>A program consists of two modules executed sequentially. Let \\(f_1(t)\\) and \\(f_2(t)\\) respectively denote the probability density functions of time taken to execute the two modules. The probability density function of the overall time taken to execute the program is given by <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2007)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(f_1(t)+f_2(t)\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(\\int_0^t f_1(x)f_2(x)dx\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(\\int_0^t f_1(x)f_2(t-x)dx\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(\\max\\{f_1(t),f_2(t)\\}\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(\\int_0^t f_1(x)f_2(t-x)dx\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/948/gate2003-60-isro2007-45\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 12,
          "question": "<p>Company X shipped 5 computer chips, 1 of which was defective. and company Y shipped 4 computer chips, 2 of which were defective. One computer chip is to be chosen uniformly at a random from the 9 chips shipped by the companies. If the chosen chip is found to be defective, what is the probability that the chip came from the company Y? <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2007)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>2/9</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>4/9</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>2/3</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>1/2</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>2/3</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/49507/isro2007-33\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 13,
          "question": "<p>In a multi-user operating system on an average, 20 requests are made to use a particular resource per hour. The arrival of requests follows a Poisson distribution. The probability that either one, three or five requests are made in 45 minutes is given by : <br><br><strong>(GATE IT 2007)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(6.9 \\times 10^6 \\times e^{-20}\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(1.02 \\times 10^6 \\times e^{-20}\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(6.9 \\times 10^3 \\times e^{-20}\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(1.02 \\times 10^3 \\times e^{-20}\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(1.02 \\times 10^6 \\times e^{-20}\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/3499/gate2007-it-57\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 14,
          "question": "<p>Suppose there are two coins. The first coin gives heads with probability \\(\\dfrac{5}{8}\\) when tossed, while the second coin gives heads with probability \\(\\dfrac{1}{4}\\). One of the two coins is picked up at random with equal probability and tossed. What is the probability of obtaining heads ? <br><br><strong>(GATE IT 2007)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(\\left(\\dfrac{7}{8}\\right)\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(\\left(\\dfrac{1}{2}\\right)\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(\\left(\\dfrac{7}{16}\\right)\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(\\left(\\dfrac{5}{32}\\right)\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(\\left(\\dfrac{7}{16}\\right)\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/3432/gate2007-it-1\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 15,
          "question": "<p>Suppose we uniformly and randomly select a permutation from the 20!\nPermutations of 1, 2,3 ,...,20. What is the probability that 2 appears at an\nearlier position than any other even number in the selected permutation? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2007)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(\\frac{1}{2}\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(\\frac{1}{10}\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(\\frac{9!}{20!}\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>None of these</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(\\frac{1}{10}\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1222/gate2007-24#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        }
      ]
    }
  ]
}